A Guide to the Correspondence of General John S. Crocker 1843-1890
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Correspondence of General John S. Crocker 1843-1890
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11312
30 items in 2 folders: Folder 1: 1843 & 1851-1859 (10 items) Folder 2: 1860-1864, 1880 & 1890 (20 items)
This collection consists of 30 items, 1843-1890, chiefly letters of John S. Crocker (1825-1890) of Cambridge, New York. Most of the letters present, accompanied by partial modern transcripts, were written by Crocker to his wife Harriet Sipperly Crocker (ten letters); Harriet's nine letters are addressed to her husband or members of her family. A few letters by other members of the Crocker family are also present.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Library purchased this collection from the History Broker, Roanoke, Virginia, May 16, 1997, and it bears no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
John S. Crocker was born in 1825 (some sources say 1820) in Cambridge, New York. His family resided for six years in Fairfax County, Virginia until returning to New York. After reading law with a prominent local attorney Crocker practiced in Cambridge between 1849 and 1859. During the 1850s Crocker was elected to the House of Representatives of the state of New York (1856), became colonel of the 30th Regiment New York State Military Forces and apparently obtained the rank of general of militia. Upon the outbreak of the Civil War Crocker volunteered for duty and became the colonel of the 93rd Regiment New York State Volunteers (the Morgan Rifles), Army of the Potomac. During the 1862 Yorktown siege Confederate forces captured and imprisoned him in Libby Prison, Richmond, Virginia, and Salisbury Prison, North Carolina. Exchanged after four months' captivity (May-August 1862), he returned to duty and served until mustered out in September 1864 on a surgeon's certificate of disability.
On March 13, 1865, he received a commission as brevet brigadier general for services during the war. General Crocker settled in Washington, D.C., and between 1867 and 1869 was elected to its board of common council and board of alderman. Appointed warden of the District of Columbia Jail in March 1869 (a position which he held to his death), Crocker had charge over the execution of Charles J. Guiteau, assassin of President James A. Garfield. Crocker died on September 14, 1890, in Washington, and was buried in Glenwood Cemetery.
David H. King, Judson Gibbs and Jay H. Northup, History of the Ninety-third Regiment, New York Volunteer Infantry, 1861-1865(Milwaukee, Wisconsin: Swain & Tate Company, 1895), pp. 493-500; Adjutant-General's Office, Official Army Register Of The Volunteer Force Of The United States Army For The Years 1861, '62, '63, '64, '65, Part 2: New York and New Jersey(Washington; Adjutant-General's Office, 1867; reprint, Gaithersburg, Maryland: Ron R. Van Sickle Military Books, 1987), 2:575; Ezra J. Warner, Generals in Blue(Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1986), 584].
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of 30 items, 1843-1890, chiefly letters of John S. Crocker (1825-1890) of Cambridge, New York. Most of the letters present, accompanied by partial modern transcripts, were written by Crocker to his wife Harriet Sipperly Crocker (ten letters); Harriet's nine letters are addressed to her husband or members of her family. A few letters by other members of the Crocker family are also present.
John and Harriet Crockers discuss local and family matters and express their love and devotion to each other. Items of interest include John's acceptance of Christianity (February 15, 1843), a love poem by Harriet (October 8, 1843), her request for mailing envelopes (March 12, 1856), regimental orders to the 30th New York militia ordering its participation at an execution (November 10, 1858), a visit to Congress (March 3, 1859), John's reaction after his release from Confederate prison (August 20, 1862), antebellum visits to Langley, Falls Church and Fairfax County, Virginia (May 25, 1851, March 3, 1859, February 20 and 23, 1860), and criticism of too many parties and balls in the midst of civil war (March 20, 1864). Also present are three court documents concerning the administration of General Crocker's estate (1890), biographical sketches, and five empty postmarked envelopes. One of these, postmarked "Philadelphia/186?, Mrs. Harriet S. Crocker, Cambridge, Washington County, N. Y.," bears on its verso two illustrated advertisements of the Cooper Shop Volunteer Refreshment Saloon, Otsego Street near the Navy Yard, Philadelphia, J. Spittall, Engraver & Printer, 409 Chestnut Street, Philadelphia.
Prominent persons mentioned or referred to in the correspondence include Senator David Colbreth Broderick (1820-1859) of California, Brevet Brigadier General Ambrose S. Cassidy (?-?), General John A. Dix (1798- 1879), President Abraham Lincoln, (1809-1865), General George B. McClellan (1826-1885), Secretary of War Edwin M. Stanton (1814-1869), and General Mariano Guadelupe Vallejo (1808-1890).
Contents List
- Letter 1843 Feb 15 (Folder 1)
  JSC to "Dear Harriet" (future wife Harriet Sipperly), North White Creek, New York: he describes his conversion to Christianity and acceptance of Jesus Christ as his personal savior
- Letter 1843 Apr 15 (Folder 1)
  JSC to "Dear Harriet" (Harriet Sipperly), North White Creek, New York: denies himself from charges by Harriet's friends and family that he is courting her only because of her wealth and defends his reputation; defends his reputation and points out that townspeople held him in high esteem as he was twice elected to public office by them
- Letter 1843 Oct 8 (Folder 1)
  Harriet Sipperly [Crocker] to "My affectionate Companion" (JSC), Schaghticoke [New York]: a badly torn (2 pieces) love letter written by this newlywed wife who misses her husband; smallpox has not yet arrived but she has been vaccinated; "there is nothing in this world I value but you"; concludes with a love poem: "Distrust me not thine own/My sighs are all for thee/On the I think alone/What ere my fate may be/If others be as fair/What air their charms to me/I neither know nor care/For thou art all to me"
- Letter 1851 May 25 (Folder 1)
  Harriet Crocker to "Dear Sister" (Anna M. Carpenter), Fairfax [Virginia]: family news; discusses strawberries, cherries, potatoes, peaches, apples, wheat, and her garden; sales of the family butter and milk
- Letter 1856 Jan 1 (Folder 1)
  Harriet S. Crocker to "My Dear Husband" (JSC), Cambridge: in this New Year's Day letter she reports on family news and her loneliness; "I pray you are having a fine time to day well enjoying yourself this winter be happy but do not forget your Savior"
- Letter 1856 March 12 (Folder 1)
  Harriet S. Crocker to "My dear husband" (JSC), Cambridge: family and local news; has been out visiting; postscript "Please fetch me a couple packages of envelopes the same size as the one on this"
- Letter 1856 Apr 3 (Folder 1)
  Harriet S. Crocker to "My Dearest Beloved John" (JSC), Cambridge: misses him ("If you cannot come home on Saturday eve send word"); general news and comments; in postscript she writes "John I hope you will not cross the river again on the ice I do not think it safe"
- Letter 1857 June 13 (Folder 1)
  JSC to "My own & best beloved" (HSC), Swifs Gothic House: a loving letter marking the occasion of their wedding anniversary ("I am reminded that today closes another of the years that have passed since the time we in the presence of God and man united hands in token of hearts united--A union of hearts which we then believed & now feel & realize to have been the result of congenial spirits, kindred thoughts & desires")
- Letter 1858 Nov 10 (Folder 1)
  Colonel John S. Crocker, Regimental Orders No. 43, Headquarters 30th Regiment New York State Military Forces, Cambridge, New York, to Captain Alvin Fish, A Company: Sheriff Hugh R. Cowen of Washington County has requested militia assistance in the execution of Martin Wallace on 1 December 1858, Salem, Washington County; JSC orders Fish to accompany his company, equipped for full military duty, to the Cambridge Valley Rail Road Station in White Creek on the day of the execution by 8:30 a.m.; Fish's company to undergo an Inspection of Arms fifteen minutes after its arrival at the station
- Letter 1859 Mar 3 (Folder 1)
  JSC to "My Dear Harriet" (HSC), Washington, D.C., w/envelope: has visited Congress on personal business and briefly describes its routine; describes his meeting with California Senator David Colbreth Broderick; mentions a rumor that a bankrupt former acquaintance named M. E. Cooke was to marry the daughter of General Mariano Guadelupe Vallejo; describes an evening ball at the Willard Hotel ("There were but a few low necked dresses & shirt sleeves... about two hundred couples present"); in postscript written March 4 he plans to visit relatives in Langley, Virginia; expresses longing to see her and their family and return to their "Swifs Cottage Home"
- Letter 1860 Feb 21 (Folder 2)
  JSC to "Dear Harriet" (HSC), Falls Church, Virginia, w/envelope: has visited family in Langley, Virginia; his cough and sore throat are much improves; discusses his business transactions; misses her and looking forward to returning home
- Letter 1860 Feb 23 (Folder 2)
  JSC to "My own Dear Harriet" (HSC), Falls Church, Fairfax [County] Virginia: hopes her health has improved (calls her "my Dear Hatta"); his health improving; expects to be home by Wednesday; promises his three sons that he will resume his routines with them "Tell little Willis Pa will soon be home to walk him to sleep again Irving must have his portfolio & Johny his music"); stayed at his sister-in-law's (Sally Ann) home but complains it was "not such a residence and location as the President of the United States will be likely to select for his residence although it is in Washington"
- Letter 1860 Dec 21 (Folder 2)
  Francis & Anna Crocker (parents of JSC ) to "Dear son and daughter," Glen Aire, Fairfax County, Virginia, w/envelope postmarked "Georgetown, Dec. 24, 1860": a mourning letter announcing the death of their daughter Aseneth Elizabeth [Crocker] Ransom from typhoid this morning; "now one Lovely Lamp is gone out but God has spoke & we must be still"
- Letter 1861 June 27 (Folder 2)
  JSC to "Mrs. Harriet S. Crocker," Cambridge [New York], w/envelope: a personal letter written upon Crocker's return home from dropping his wife and family off at a Healing Springs; has arrived at their Cottage Home; misses her and their sons Irving, Willis and Johny; "I have got my troops out on the road mending the ways a little" [JSC had volunteered for duty June 1861 and was appointed inspector and mustering officer of volunteers; see David H. King, Judson Gibbs and Jay H. Northup, History of the Ninety- third Regiment, New York Volunteer Infantry, 1861-1865(Milwaukee, Wisconsin: Swain & Tate Company, 1895), p. 496]; a letter from her sister Sally Ann arrived, he opened it and found all are well
- Letter 1862 Mar 5 (Folder 2)
  JSC telegram (American Telegraph Company), New York, to Mrs. H. S. Crocker, Eagle Bridge: informs her that his regiment [93rd Regiment New York State Volunteers] will leave for Washington "tomorrow Thursday"
- Letter 1862 Apr 16 (Folder 2)
  Harriet S. Crocker to "My Dear and Affectionate Husband" (JSC), Cambridge, w/envelope: local and family news including mention of the increase in size of a stream in front of their house that now threatens to flood a foot bridge; asks if he can visit home on June 13 (their wedding anniversary); asks of if Major [Ambrose L.] Cassidy has any photographs of himself and (Brevet Brigadier General Ambrose S. Cassidy?) and George B. McClellan that he could send to her; envelope note "These reached Camp just after Col. C's [Crocker] capture--were returned to Mrs. Crocker" [see Adjutant-General's Office, Official Army Register, 2:575 and Ezra J. Warner, Generals in Blue(Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1986), 583]
- Letter 1862 Aug 20 (Folder 2)
  JSC to "My Beloved Harriette" (HSC), Washington, D.C., w/envelope: has been released from Libby Prison after four month's imprisonment, mentions reporting to General John A. Dix (1798-1879) at Fort Monroe, Virginia; will call upon the Secretary of War (Edwin M. Stanton) and the President (Abraham Lincoln) tomorrow
- Letter 1863 Sep 21 (Folder 2)
  Phoebe Sipperly (sister of Harriet S. Crocker) to "My dear Jennie(?), Cambridge: apologizes for not being able to visit her owing to the sudden illness of John S. Crocker last week while traveling by boat from Albany to New York City, "he was seized with vomiting and cramping which continued during the night" but is slowly recovering
- Letter 1864 Mar 1 (Folder 2)
  Harriet S. Crocker to "My Dear Husband" (JSC), Cambridge: is concerned for him as she has just read in the Troy Times that the Army of the Potomac was on the march; "It is like tearing a cord from my heart when you leave for the Army"; family and local news; dreamed the rebels were near their home
- Letter 1864 March 20 (Folder 2)
  Harriet S. Crocker to "My Dear Husband" (JSC), Cambridge, w/envelope: local and family news; bilious and scarlet fever in the area, several residents sick or have died; a Doctor Wallace [possibly Assistant Surgeon Theodore C. Wallace, 93rd New York; see Adjutant-General's Office, Official Army Register, 2:575] arrived with two horses and one contraband [a runaway slave now his personal hired servant], he has resigned from the army due to deafness; complains about the large number of balls and parties during this civil war, "The most terrible war ever recorded in History"; says a friend saw an engraving of JSC in New York on Broadway with the caption "Gen. Crocker"
- News article 1880 Apr 3 (Folder 2)
  --[this date is a typographical error as it refers to the assassination of President James A. Garfield which occurred in 1881 and his assassin hanged in 1882] electrostatic typescript, Daily Critic, Washington, D.C., Saturday, April 3, 1880 news article "General John S. Crocker/The Popular and Efficient Warden of the U. S. Jail--His Excellent Military Services--His Official Career Sketch and Short Biography"
- Court document post 1890 Sep 19 (Folder 2)
  Court document "Exhibit A/In the Superior Court of the District of Columbia Holding a Special Term for Orphan Court business In Re Estate of John S. Crocker Deceased": JSC's heirs at law (Harriet S. Crocker, Irving M. Crocker, and Willis S. Crocker) attest their consent of JSC's will and last testament being probated and administration of his estate; verso includes assent of John S. Crocker, Jr. and other family members
- Court document 1890 Oct 25 (Folder 2)
  Court document, Washington, D.C., "Estate of John S. Crocker, deceased": receipt for appraisal of JSC's personal property; signed James W. Rateaffe(?), Appraiser
- Court document 1890 Oct 25 (Folder 2)
  Court document "Supreme Court of the District of Columbia, Special Term for Orphans' Court Business": itemized bill and payment receipt for registration of the will of John S. Crocker deceased; signed L. P. Wright, Register of Wills